William T. Pheiffer Papers
William T. Pheiffer Papers
1921-1973
Pheiffer, William T. (William Townsend), 1898-
7 linear ft.
Papers of the American lawyer, legislator. Republican member of the U.S. House of Representatives from New York, 1941-1943; U.S. Ambassador to the Dominican Republic, 1950s. Collection contains correspondence, articles, clippings, legislative records, photographs, and speeches related to Pheiffer's legal career and legislative term, the Republican National Committee, the Eisenhower campaign, and the Dominican Republic.
149331
Biographical History
William T. Pheiffer (1898-1986) was an American lawyer and legislator. He served in the United States Army during World War I and then received his law degree from the University of Oklahoma in 1919. He was elected as a Republican member of the U.S. House of Representatives from New York, serving from 1941 to 1943. He served in the military again during World War II (1943-1944), after which he was appointed counsel to the Petroleum Administration for War, a position he held until 1945. President Eisenhower appointed Pheiffer U.S. Ambassador to the Dominican Republic in 1953, where he served until 1957.
The Julius Garfinckel who appears in the correspondence was Pheiffer's maternal uncle, and a successful merchant and philanthropist from Syracuse, New York.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The William T. Pheiffer Papers contains correspondence, articles, clippings, legislative records, photographs, and speeches related to Pheiffer's legal career and legislative term, the Republican National Committee, the Eisenhower campaign, and the Dominican Republic.
The collection is subdivided chronologically, according to phases in Pheiffer's career. Private life, early career and personal contains family correspondence and material relating to Pheiffer's years as a practicing lawyer in Texas. Public service career (I) material relates to Pheiffer's congressional service as a representative from New York, from 1941-1943, including elections, fundraising, bills and other items. Private life, transition period refers to Pheiffer's work as a member of the Petroleum Administration for War and then as an attorney in private practice; included here is material relating to the Eisenhower campaign. Public service career (II) is almost entirely concerned with his years as Ambassador to the Dominican Republic, inluding correspondence, clippings, speeches and other items. Material in Private life, later career reflects Pheiffer's return to private practice of law.
Memorabilia contains election posters and photographs.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is subdivided roughly chronologically, beginning with Pheiffer's early private life, followed by his first public service phase, his private life, transitional phase, his second stint in public service (including his Ambassadorship), and finally his later private life. Within each series, material does not appear to be in any particular order, and may still be in original order.
Subject and Genre Headings
New York State; Politics, government and public administration; Pheiffer, William T. (William Townsend), 1898-; Republican National Committee (U.S.); Republican Party (U.S.: 1854- ); Ambassadors -- United States.; Political campaigns.; Lawyers -- United States.; Legislators -- United States.; Politicians -- United States.; Dominican Republic -- Foreign relations -- United States.; United States -- Diplomatic and consular service -- Dominican Republic.; United States -- Foreign relations -- Dominican Republic.; United States -- Politics and government -- 1933-1945.; Articles.; Bills (legislative records); Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Photographs.; Speeches (documents); Ambassadors.; Diplomats.; Lawyers.; Legislators.; Politicians.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of William T. Pheiffer, 1964.
Gift of William T. Pheiffer Estate, 1986.
Inventory
- Private life, early career and personal
  - Correspondence
    - General, 1921-1936 (Box 1)
    - Garfinkel, Julius, 1921-1936; uncle; 26 folders (Box 1)
    - Pfeiffer, Susan (Garfinkel), 1924; 1933-1934,; 1936; mother (Box 1)
    - William T. Pheiffer, 1933; 1935,; 1936 (Box 1)
    - Texas Bar Association, Sept. 1934-Sept. 1935; 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Amarillo Bar Association, 1928; 1930,; 1932,; 1934-1938; 4 folders (Box 1)
    - Law practice, 1939 (Box 1)
    - Beckwith and Van Slyck, Dec. 1939-July 1940; 4 folders (Box 1)
- Public service career (I)
  - House of Representatives
    - Re-election, Jan. 1940-Nov. 16, 1940; 8 folders (Box 2)
    - Post-election, Nov. 18, 1940-Dec. 31, 1940; 6 folders (Box 2)
    - First term, Jan. 1941-Oct. 31, 1942; 3 folders (Box 2)
    - First term/re-election, Nov. 1942-Dec. 1942; 6 folders (Box 2)
    - Bills and resolutions, 1941-1942 (Box 2)
    - Campaign literature, 1940-1942; undated; 5 folders (Box 2)
    - Election returns, first and second elections, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Fundraising, Mar. 23, 1940-Aug. 7, 1940; May Day Ball (Box 2)
    - Legislation, Mar. 1942-Dec. 1942; cooperative apartment; 3 folders (Box 2)
    - List of correspondence, 1942; 2 folders (Box 3)
    - General correspondence, Jan 1940-June 1943; undated; 7 folders (Box 3)
    - Clippings, 1940-1942; 3 folders (Box 3)
    - Names and addresses, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - O'Conner, Hon. John, 1940-1942; 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Printed material, 1940-1942 (Box 3)
    - Pro America, 1940 (Box 3)
    - Speeches (WTP), 1941-1942 (Box 3)
- Private life, transition period
  - General correspondence, Jan. 1943-Jan. 1948 (Box 3)
  - Petroleum Administration for War, June 1944-March 1945; correspondence (Box 3)
  - Dr. Pepper Company, June 1944-Jan. 1946; correspondence (Box 3)
  - Republican National Committee
    - Correspondence, Oct. 1945-April 1953 (Box 3)
    - Names and addresses, 1952; 4 folders (Box 3)
    - Speeches (WTP), 1945 (Box 3)
  - Eisenhower campaign organization, March 1952-July 1952; correspondence (Box 3)
  - Yuba Consolidated Industries, Oct. 1951-May 1965; correspondence (Box 3)
- Public service career (II)
  - Dominican Republic
    - Correspondence, Jan 1953-Sept. 1953; 16 folders (Box 3)
    - Correspondence, Oct. 1953-July 7, 1955; 44 folders (Box 4)
    - Correspondence, July 8, 1955-May 1957; 41 folders (Box 5)
    - Correspondence, June 1957-Nov. 1957; undated; 5 folders (Box 6)
    - Articles, 1953-1960; 1965; 5 folders (Box 6)
    - "Bible" Memos, June 26, 1953-Nov. 23, 1954; 4 folders (Box 6)
    - Clippings
      - General, May 1953-1957; 8 folders (Box 6)
      - New York Herald Tribune, Sept. 14, 1953 (Box 6)
      - General Hood, 1954 (Box 6)
      - Westbrook Pegler, 1954 (Box 6)
      - Galindez case, 1958 (Box 6)
      - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 6)
    - Coronet Article, 1957 (Box 6)
    - Printed material, 1953-1957 (Box 6)
    - Speeches (WTP), 1953-1957; 3 folders (Box 6)
    - Speeches (by others), 1957 (Box 6)
- Private life, later career
  - General, Aug. 1957-Dec. 1957; correspondence (Box 6)
  - Law Practice
    - Correspondence, Jan. 1958; 1970,; 1973,; 1979; 20 folders (Box 6)
    - Speeches, 1958-1960 (Box 6)
  - Correspondence, undated (Box 6)
  - Printed material
    - Clippings, 1947-1966; 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Miscellaneous, 1935-1971; undated (Box 6)
  - Speeches
    - By others, 1947-1949; 1978 (Box 6)
    - WTP, 1926; 1948,; 1952 (Box 6)
- Memorabilia
  - Photographs (Oversize 7)
  - Election posters and ballots (Oversize 7)